Okay so we are in the middle of עין ה׳ עמוד ב׳
*Ayin Hey Amud Beis* still trying to figure out what this ברייתא
braisa *Braisah* of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. *Rebbi Eliezer* means
and
we have another possibility. כי אתא רבין אמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן *Ki Ata Ravin amar Rebbi Chiya bar Abba amar
Rebbi Yochanan* ואמרי לה אמר רבי אבא בר זבדא אמר רבי חנינא
*veamri lah amar Rebbi Abba bar Zavda amar Rebbi Chanina* ואמרי לה
אמר רבי יעקב בר אידי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי levi *veamri
lah amar Rebbi Yaakov bar Idi amar Rebbi Yehoshua ben Levi* three
possible trades for one tradition. שלוש מחלוקת בדבר *shalosh machlokes badavar*. What
דבר *davar*
is
unclear. It's a מחלוקת ראשונים *machlokes Rishonim* about whether the thing that's
actually talking about the איסור issur *issur* for כותים kutim, *Kutim* to
marry Jews or for כותי בכותית *Kuti beKutit*. ריטב״א *Ritva* brings both
and explains how it might work that all three of the possibilities
which we'll see in a minute are about כותי בכותית *Kuti beKutit*
which is the ברייתא braisa, *Braisah* that we're talking about. The one
that he ends up accepting and I think the more likely it
and he argues that's a better explanation is that the first two
possibilities are about כותי בישראל *Kuti beYisrael* and only the last possibility
in this tradition is כותי בכותית *Kuti beKutit* which is the thing
we're actually talking about. So רבי ישמעאל סבר *Rebbi Yishmael savar* כותים
גרי אריות הן *Kutim gerei arayos hein*. So רבי ישמעאל *Rebbi Yishmael*
is the first opinion in this tradition. He thinks that the כותים
*Kutim* are actually bad converts, their conversion didn't take. רמב״ן
*Ramban* goes a little bit crazy over here but we're not going
to go into that because in יבמות *Yevamos* we hold that גרי
אריות *gerei arayos* are good גרים gerim, *geirim* so why is גרי
אריות *gerei arayos* apparently not a good גירות *geirus* over here? והכהנים
שנטמעו בהן כהנים kohanim פסולים היו *vehakohanim shenitme'u bahen Kohanim psulim hayu*.
They're also this tradition is also talking about these כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*
that lived among the Samaritans as רש״י *Rashi* points out
and those כהנים kohanim, שנטמעו בהן כהנים Kohanim פסולים היו *Kohanim shenitme'u
bahen Kohanim psulim hayu* שנאמר ויעשו להם מקצותם כהני במות *shenemar vayaasu
lahem miktzosam Kohanei bamos*.
They made a few of the few of the כהנים *Kohanim* of
them במות *bamos*, they made altars outside the temple. ואמר רבה בר
בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן *veamar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rebbi
Yochanan* and we explained what exactly is the דרשה drasha *drasha* here
on this פסוק pasuk *pasuk* from מלכים ב׳ *Melachim Beis* מן הקוצים
שבעם *min hakotzim shebaam* from the thorns in the nation so the
bad ones, פסולים *psulim*. ומשום הכי פסלינהו *umeshum hachi paslinhu*. That's why
they're פסול psul, *pasul*.
Well having altars outside the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* was nothing unusual
in those days. Yeah but not in an official capacity.
According to חז״ל *Chazal* this is already אסור *assur* at this point.
Of course it's not uncommon.
Yes yes yes but they were all over ספר מלכים *Sefer Melachim*.
Yes absolutely.
So that's one possible. רבי עקיבא סבר *Rebbi Akiva savar* רבי עקיבא
*Rebbi Akiva* is the second opinion in this tradition. כותים גרי אמת
הן *Kutim gerei emes hein* that the Samaritans actually had a good
conversion. והכהנים שנטמעו בהן כהנים כשרים היו *vehakohanim shenitme'u bahen Kohanim ksheirim
hayu* and actually the כהנים *Kohanim* that lived among them were good
כהנים *Kohanim* שנאמר ויעשו להם מקצותם כהני במות *shenemar vayaasu lahem miktzosam
Kohanei bamos* because it refers to these כהנים *Kohanim* that were there.
But how can they be bad things
to make these במות *bamos*?
Yeah but it doesn't פסול psul *posul* the כהנים *Kohanim*. Right understood.
It didn't פסול pasul.
*posul* the כהנים *Kohanim* in the first case either, we're just we
דרש *darshan* the פסוק *pasuk* as saying that those כהנים *Kohanim* were
not good כהנים *Kohanim*.
This דרשה drasha
*drasha* we'll see in a second. ואמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן *veamar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rebbi Yochanan* explains this
part of the tradition this way. מן הבחירים שבעם *min habechirim shebaam*
not מן הקוצים *min hakotzim* but מן הבחירים *min habechirim*. So מקצותם
*miktzosam* isn't as a play on קוץ *kotz*, it's מקצת *miktzas* ah
the nice ones. ואלא מפני מה אסרום *ve'ela mipnei mah asrum* the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks or the tradition itself asks. So why are
they אסור *assur*?
Why can't you marry them, why can't they marry each other maybe?
מפני שהיו מיבמים את הארוסות ופוטרים את הנשואות *mipnei shehayu meyabmim es
haarusos ufotrim es hanesuos*. So
they would only practice יבום yibum. *yibum* with a widow who had
not for whom נישואין *nisuim* had not been done and they would
not do יבום yibum, *yibum* for a woman who was only betrothed
and not yet been fully married.
The opposite of what we do.
Which is the opposite of what we do and is problematic. Now
how problematic is it? It's only problematic a particular way. רש״י *Rashi*
says already here at the top of עין ו׳ עמוד א׳ *Ayin
Vav Amud Aleph* ופוטרים את הנשואות מן החליצה *ufotrim es hanesuos min
hachalitza* ולרבי עקיבא בני חייבי לאוין ממזרים mamzerim הם *ulerabbi Akiva bnei
chayavei lavin mamzeirim heim*. רבי עקיבא *Rebbi Akiva* already has his special
his special שיטה shita *shita* that when you have a forbidden relationship
from an איסור issur לאו *issur lav* as opposed to an איסור
כרת *issur kares* that creates a ממזר mamzer, *mamzer*. מאי דרשי *Mai
darshi*? So
what is the what is the דרשה drasha *drasha* that the כותים
*Kutim* used to get to this strange opinion?
They go back to the פסוק *pasuk* in the they go back
to the פסוק *pasuk* in the תורה Torah, *Torah*. So the whole
פסוק *pasuk* in the תורה Torah *Torah* is כי ישבו אחים יחדיו
ומת אחד מהם ובן אין לו לא lo. תהיה אשת המת החוצה
לאיש זר יבמה יבא עליה ולקחה לו לאשה ויבמה *ki yeshvu achim
yachdav umas echad mehem uven ein lo lo sihiyeh eshes hamess hachutza
l'ish zar yevamah yavo aleha velakacha lo l'isha veyibma*. So they go
into the phrase of the פסוק *pasuk* לא תהיה אשת המת החוצה
לאיש זר *lo sihiyeh eshes hamess hachutza l'ish zar* she should not
go out to a stranger. היכא דנפקא חוצה היא לא תהיה לאיש
זר tihyeh l'ish zar. *heicha denafkah chutza hee lo sihiyeh l'ish zar*.
The one who sat outside, she shouldn't marry an outside man, she
requires יבום. So that is a woman who has not yet gone
into the house, an ארוסה, arusah, she requires יבום. אבל הכא דלא
יתבא חוצה Aval hacha d'lo yatba chutzah תהיה לאיש זר. A woman
who has not sat outside, she sat inside, she was fully married
to the man, she doesn't need יבום, she can go out to
an איש זר. ish zar. But Rabbi Akiva, who holds that this
creates a פסול, pasul. לטעמיה, letameih, דאמר יש ממזר מחייבי לאוין. d'amar
yesh mamzer m'chayvei lavin.
So we saw this already in רש"י, Rashi, he's just pointing us
forward to this part of the גמרא Gemara which points us to
Rabbi Akiva's שיטה and explains what the פסול is. ויש אומרים, V'yesh
omrim,
the third opinion in the שלוש מחלוקות, shalosh machlokot, לפי שאין בקיאין
בדקדוקי מצוות, lefi she'ein baki'in b'dikdukei mitzvos, that the Samaritans are not
so careful about the details of the laws.
Neither are most people.
Neither are most people? Yeah, I mean, so we're going to see
that this means a specific thing.
But yeah, it's a for us it's a strange thing because not
that many people are really so בקיאין בדקדוקי מצוות. baki'in b'dikdukei mitzvos.
And we're not considered פסול.
We're definitely not considered פסול.
Okay, גמרא Gemara asks, who's this ויש אומרים? v'yesh omrim? There's two
opinions with the name and then there's one opinion without a name.
אמר רב אידי בר אבין, Amar Rav Iddi bar Abin, who I
believe was one of the traders? No.
No,
his son was maybe or somebody else named Iddi.
ורבי אלעזר היא. V'Rabbi Elazar hee. So the גרסא girsah here actually
says רבי אליעזר.
That's based on מהרש"ל. Maharshal.
רש"ש Rashash here changes the text to רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, which
makes more sense in our סוגיא. sugya. That's noted on the side
of
the
Oz VeHadar edition. Does anyone know who רש"ש Rashash is?
I mean, I don't know what it stands for, but
so רש"ש Rashash is רבי שמואל שטראשון, Rabbi Shmuel Strashun,
who was a student of the חיי אדם. Chayei Adam. שטראשון Strashun
was not actually his family name, he married a שטראשון, Strashun, which
was a very, very wealthy family in Lithuania and he took on
that family name. He was actually called זאסקעוויצער. Zaskevitzer.
And in the when the חיי אדם Chayei Adam refers to him,
he calls him זאסקעוויצער, Zaskevitzer, but in the וילנא ש"ס Vilna Shas
he's called he's called שטראשון. Strashun. I think I'd heard that he's
actually the only one who was alive when the וילנא ש"ס Vilna
Shas was printed. I don't think that's true, I think he died
a few years beforehand. There's somebody else, there's like one person in
the וילנא ש"ס Vilna Shas who was alive when it was printed.
There's a funny story though, the רש"ש Rashash is very popular, he's
at the back of most גמרות, gemaras, sometimes in the newer ones
he's put in as part of the ילקוט מפרשים. Yalkut Mefarshim.
But in the old ones he has his own space.
There's a story that רב שלמה זלמן Rav Shlomo Zalman heard somebody
making fun of the רש"ש, Rashash, he says, you know the רש"ש,
Rashash, because he was so wealthy, he paid to have his הגהות
hagahot put into the וילנא ש"ס. Vilna Shas. And רב שלמה זלמן
Rav Shlomo Zalman was hearing, he commented, I would also pay to
the רש"ש Rashash to have the רש"ש Rashash put into the וילנא
ש"ס. Vilna Shas.
So
anyway, this is רבי
אלעזר היא, Rabbi Elazar hee, דתניא, d'tanya, so there's a ברייתא braisa.
that proves this. מצת כותים מותרת, Matzat kutim muteret,
the מצה matzah made by a Samaritan is מותרת muteret on פסח,
Pesach, ואדם יוצא בה ידי חובתו בפסח, v'adam yotzei bah yedei chovato
b'Pesach, and actually works to eat מצה, matzah, you don't need to
eat anything else. Unlike other things, as רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos
point out, which you could eat which are מותר mutar on פסח
Pesach but you're not יוצא ידי חובתו בהם. yotzei yedei chovato bahem.
Even though they observe פסח Pesach on a different day from us?
Apparently they make good מצה matzah and they observe שימור. shimur. Tasty,
really.
So רבי אלעזר אוסר. Rabbi Elazar oser. So in that, in that
ברייתא, braisa רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says no, you can't eat that
מצה, matzah, that's the thing where they're not בקיאין בדקדוקי מצוות. baki'in
b'dikdukei mitzvos. לפי שאין בקיאין בדקדוקי מצוות Lefi she'ein baki'in b'dikdukei mitzvos
says the says the ברייתא. Braita But to continue, רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, כל מצוה שהחזיקו בה כותים
הרבה מדקדקים בה יותר מישראל. kol mitzvah she'hecheziku bah kutim harbe m'dakdekim
bah yoter mi'Yisrael.
When they when they followed מצוות, mitzvos, they followed them really well
and they did it, they did them better than we did them.
So it's just that's irrelevant to our point, but it's part of
this ברייתא Braita and it's an interesting idea that people who take
on certain things really do them, which is I think real even
בזמן הזה. bizman hazeh. ולהכא, V'la'hacha,
so fine, we saw that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says that there's
אין בקיאין בדקדוקי מצוות ein baki'in b'dikdukei mitzvos by כותים, but here,
מאי אין בקיאין? mai ein baki'in? What is the thing that they're
actually not בקי baki by? Whether they're בקי baki by מצה matzah
or not doesn't doesn't reflect on their יחוס. yichus.
We answer, לפי שאין בקיאין בתורת קידושין וגירושין, lefi she'ein baki'in b'torat
kiddushin v'geirushin,
that they actually don't know the rules properly of how marriages work.
So they might think that someone has been properly divorced and then
there would be a ממזר, or they might think that someone wasn't
married properly, they don't need a גט, get, even though they do
actually need a גט get and that creates ממזרות mamzeirut later on
and so there's all sorts of ספק ממזר safek mamzer flowing around
in there and we see that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar already holds
that ספק בספק safek b'safek is a big problem. Which is why
he would say כותי בכותי kuti b'kuti is a problem. We
have
two more.
בדקדוקי מצוות Dikdukei mitzvos here doesn't mean those whole categories.
בדקדוקי מצוות Dikdukei mitzvos here means like there's details of these rules.
So these rules? קידושין וגירושין. Kiddushin v'geirushin. Yeah. So why
is
it referring
to דקדוקי מצוות *diyukei mitzvos*, I would say?
So the tradition that we have about כותים *Kutim* says they're not
בקיאים *beki'im* in דקדוקי מצוות *diyukei mitzvos*, and that's why there is
a problem of marriage with them, and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* explains
that tradition in this context as referring specifically to issues of אישות
*ishus*.
Yeah, I understand it, but it's just a weird way of saying
it. דקדוקי מצוות *Diyukei mitzvos* really just means like one specific thing.
Does it? It could mean a broad it's very broad. Isn't that
what you said first? That it's like שאין בקיאין בדקדוקי מצוות *she'ein
beki'in
b'diyukei mitzvos* is a very broad category that they don't have the
details down.
And so it's like, what are the details they don't have down?
Certain things, not others, and apparently we hold according to this יש
אומרים *yeish omrim* that the details they don't have down include the
details of אישות *ishus*.
That makes sense in terms of intermarriage and loss of
potential...
It is it would make more sense for the tradition to have
שאין יודעים טיב גיטין וקידושין *she'ein yodim tiv gittin v'kiddushin*. Right, exactly.
That might make more sense, but that's not what it has, and
there's like, this is a widely transmitted tradition clearly because there's three
different ברייתות *baraisos* for it.
So, we have two other possibilities which are not in the שלוש
מחלוקת *shalosh machlokos* of why the כותים *Kutim* are problematic. אמר רב
Rav נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה Rabba bar Avuha *Amar Rav Nachman
amar Rabbah bar Avuha*: ממזר מאחותו וממזר מאשת איש נתערבו בהן *mamzer
mei'achoso u'mamzer mei'eishes ish nit'arvu bahen*. So here, נתערבו בהן *nit'arvu bahen*.
So there were two people who would have caused ממזר *mamzer* problems
who actually became part of that community and that creates ממזר *mamzer*
problems in the whole community.
The גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* asks: why is this אמורא amora *Amora* telling
us about both of these? מאי קמשמע לן *mai kamashma lan*? יש
ממזר מחייבי כריתות *yeish mamzer mei'chayavei krisos*? Maybe he's teaching us that
ממזר *mamzer* comes from חייבי כריתות *chayavei krisos* as opposed to חייבי
לאווין *chayavei lavin* or as opposed to מיתת בית דין din *misas
beis din*. So if that's the case, למה לי תרתי *lama li
tarti*? Why is he teaching us both? Why is he teaching us
both אשת אח *eishes ach* and why is he teaching us, sorry,
both ממזר מאחותו *mamzer mei'achoso* and מאשת איש *mei'eishes ish*? Why is
it incest and adultery? I only need to know one of those
happened.
The answer being מעשה ma'aseh שהיה כך היה *ma'aseh shehayah kach hayah*.
That it actually did happen, and this is a historical point that
there was really a product of a person who was a product
of incest and a person who was a product of adultery, and
both of those people became part of this Samaritan community and so
that's why he says both.
Another possibility, ורבא אמר עבד ושפחה נתערבו בהן *v'Rava amar eved v'shifchah
nit'arvu bahen*. That there's a different set of יחוס yichus *yichus* problems
that are created by different people who became part of the Samaritan
community. איסורא משום מאי *issura mishum mai*? משום שפחה *mishum shifchah*. So
what's really the problem? Because of the שפחה *shifchah*, because when someone
has a when a free person has a child with a female
slave, that creates the person who you think might be free but
really isn't and then creates the ממזר *mamzer* problems. למה לי תרתי
*lama li tarti*? So we have the same question. Why are you
teaching עבד ושפחה *eved v'shifchah*? If שפחה *shifchah* is the only problem,
why are you telling me about the עבד *eved* who became part
of the community as well? מעשה שהיה כך היה *ma'aseh shehayah kach
hayah*. Same answer, historical fact. You don't mess with historical fact. Okay,
that's the end of that סוגיא sugya *sugya*. Now we have a
new משנה Mishna *Mishnah*.
This משנה Mishna *Mishnah* is about doing something that we really don't
do anymore, which is about checking people's יחוס yichus *yichus*. I guess
we do do this, but not in the way that they describe.
Not in the way that they describe, I think,
because we don't פסקן *pasken* this way. There's a שיטת חכמים *shitas
chachamim* which comes up in the סוגיא sugya, *sugya* which says that
everyone has חזקת כשרות chezkat kashrut. *chezkas kashrus*.
Why we do this, why the why the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah* says
to do this, or maybe we do do this
okay, it's in the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam*, I don't know. So
why we do this, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* which is brought by
רמב"ן Ramban *Ramban* says that it's a קנס knas, *knas*, that there
is a specific purpose to this rule, which is let me read
it out of the ריטב"א Ritva *Ritva* who cites it: זו קנס
שקנסו
*zo knas she'kansu*. This is something that חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* required of
us as some sort of punishment, כדי שיהא אדם דבק בשבטו ובמשפחתו
*kedei sheyei adam davek b'shivto u'v'mishpachto*. So that a person would cleave
to his tribe a man would cleave to his tribe and to
his family. This is a way of keeping you attached to the
people you're supposed to be attached to. פירוש *peirush*, says ריטב"א *Ritva*,
בדין הוא שלא יהו צריכין בדיקה bedika. כלל klal *badin hu shelo
yehu tzrichin bdika klal*. It's not logical that anyone really needs to
check for יחוס yichus *yichus* issues. לא לפסולי כהונה Kehunah, ולא לפסולי
ממזרות Mamzerut, *lo l'psulei kehunah v'lo l'psulei mamzerus*. Not for issues of
פסולי כהונה Psulei Kehunah *psulei kehunah* and not for issues of actual
ממזרות mamzerut *mamzerus*. אלא שקנסו חכמים להצריך בדיקה bdika כדי שיהא כל
אחד דבק בשבטו ומשפחתו הברורה לו *ela shekansu chachamim l'hatzrich bdika kedei
sheyei kol echad davek b'shivto u'mishpachto habrura lo*. Because they need to
be closer to their family, ולא יהא צריך לטרוח ולבדוק, שקנסו יותר
בלויים וכו' *v'lo yei tzarich litro'ach v'livdok, shekansu yoser b'levi'im v'chulei*. So
the point is there's some idea here expressed in this rabbinic law
that people ought to be closer with their families. I think the
רלב"ג *Ralbag* has this as well as one of his תועלות *to'alos*
in בראשית *Bereishis* that people should marry into their family.
Wait a second, I mean, I thought the whole point or at
least one of the nine reasons why we celebrate ט"ו באב *Tu
B'Av* was because הותרו שבטים לבוא
זה בזה *hutru
shevatim lavo zeh b'zeh*. So and here so here we're reversing that?
Don't know. Don't know.
The ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* doesn't hold that way I guess. Not sure.
I think we just...
So not everybody explains it this way because תוספות Tosafot disagree as
to that ירושלמי to make sense, for that ירושלמי to make sense
this משנה Mishna has to refer both to פסולי כהונה Psulei Kehunah
and to פסולי קהל, Psulei Kahal, which is how רמב"ן Ramban and
his students held. תוספות Tosafot say no, no, no, this has nothing
to do with פסולי קהל, Psulei Kahal, this has nothing to do
with ממזרות, this is only about פסולי כהונה Psulei Kehunah and they
explain the whole thing slightly differently. So we'll see that in a
minute. משנה Mishna goes as follows:
הנושא אשה כהנת, Hanoise Isha Kehenet, so one who is... it's רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both say this is a כהן Kohen who's
marrying a woman, צריך לבדוק אחריה ארבע אמהות. Tzarich livdok achareha arba
imahot. He has to check four mothers. And now we're going to
have a nice chart. You mean grandparents?
He means to go back a generation?
We're going to see שהן שמונה, shehen shemonah, so it's four which
are eight, which is more than two generations. So we'll start at
the bottom. We have a woman
here. ארבע אמהות שהן שמונה. Arba imahot shehen shemonah.
אמא ואם אמא, ima ve'em ima,
so I think that's one which is two. ואם אבי אמא Ve'em
avi ima ואמא. ve'ima.
So this is אבי אמא, avi ima, so we have אם אבי
אמא ואמא.
em avi
ima ve'ima, Oh my goodness. ואם אביה, Ve'em aviha, so then we
have אביה aviha over here. So אם אביה ואמא em aviha ve'ima,
ואם
אבי אביה ve'em avi aviha ואמא. ve'ima.
Oh my goodness. This is not how
people get
married today. Just circle the ones that we do. It's too
many. אבי אמא Avi ima you
don't. Squares
are men.
Just do it that way,
it'll
be
easier. Yeah.
That one we...
like in real life? No, yeah... oh sorry, I will circle them
in a minute. Let me finish ואמא. ve'ima So I will circle
the pairs in green. Okay, so we have אמא ואם אמא, ima
v'em ima. אם אבי אמא em avi ima ואמא, ve'ima. אם אביה
em aviha ואמא, ve'ima.
אם אבי אביה ואמא. em avi aviha ve'ima. ארבע שהן שמונה. Arba
shehen shemonah. So two generations on each side for that. That's like
one, two, three, four.
Nobody would be
able to
get married today at that level
because all the records were lost in the שואה. Shoah. I had
my...
I had my parents do כתובה ketubah before I was married.
But on all sides going back so far?
Right. And actually by the time the rabbi knew my maternal lineage
it was deemed okay.
Wow.
Yeah.
This is a little much. Okay. לוויה וישראלית Leviyah ve'Yisraelit continues the
משנה, Mishna מוסיפין עליהן עוד אחת mosifin aleihen od achat
and the גמרא Gemara, is going to explain what that means and
it doesn't mean one, it means two or four. There's a different...
there are two different גרסאות girsa'ot in the משנה Mishna here. One
is לוויה וישראלית, Leviyah ve'Yisraelit, which is what רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot, have.
The ספרדים Sephardim have לויים וישראלים, Leviyim ve'Yisraelim, which is what leads
us to the difference of opinion about whether the משנה Mishnah is
talking about פסולי כהונה psulei khuna or פסולי קהל Psulei Kahal as
well.
I see, so they have to do one more? You think these
two...
so okay, so according to תוספות, Tosafot תוספות Tosafot explain that when
a כהן Kohen is marrying a woman from a non-כהניק Kohanic lineage,
from outside of the כהונה, kehuna. those people are not so careful
about their כהניק Kohanic lineage and so you need to check even
further to make sure that it's okay for the כהן Kohen to
marry the לוויה. Leviyah. If we're saying לויים וישראלים, Leviyim ve'Yisraelim,
then it's just an issue of ממזרות and it's this... and those
people are and it's just
a קנס, it's a way of furthering the point that when a
ישראל Yisrael marries a ישראלית Yisraelit they have to make sure that
everything is okay. It's unclear. It's a little bit problematic that explanation.
תוספות Tosafot explanation makes more sense here that when a כהן Kohen
marries a כהנת, Kohenet, so when a כהן Kohen marries his third
cousin from another כהן Kohen family, he only has to check so
far. When he's marrying someone outside his family which is less careful
about whether that child can marry a כהן, Kohen, he has to
check a slightly further just to make sure it's okay that he's
not going to have children who are פסולים לכהונה. psulim l'kehunah.
Okay, so it's not talking about a regular ישראל Yisrael marrying another
regular
ישראל?
Yisrael? According to גאוני ספרד Geonei Sfarad it does.
Okay, and again the reason why you'd have to be more careful
for that?
Let's see. Give me a minute.
דכן סגי יותר בלויים וישראלים מן הכהנים לפי שאין מדקדקים כל כך
ביחוסן ואינם מידבקים במשפחותיהם.
dechen sagi yoter b'levi'im v'yisre'elim min hakohenim lefi she-ein m'dakdekim
kol kach b'yichusan v'einam m'dabkim b'mishpachoteihem. That כהנים are more careful about
their יחוס yichus already. Non-כהנים are not so careful about their יחוס
yichus. because it's less important. There's fewer problems and it creates it
like once it's mixed in there's fewer once what's if we have
problems can be mixed in and solved in different ways outside of
the כהונה. kehuna כהונה kehuna, has much stricter rules. And so they
were just less careful. And so if a לוי levi is going
to marry a לוי levi or ישראל yisrael marrying a לויה leviyah
or a ישראל yisrael is going to marry a ישראלית, yisraelit, they
were they were
they made a כנס knas that you have to do more because
you were bad at doing this before. You had all sorts of
יחוס yichus? problems that you didn't know about apparently, according to רמב"ן
Ramban and ריטב"א following him. So, it's the רמב"ן Ramban both in
the חידושים Chiddushim
and in the מלחמות Milchamot apparently.
So, משנה Mishnah, continues. You do this בדיקה. bdika. אין בודקים לא
מן המזבח ולמעלה. ein bodkim lo min hamizbe'ach u'l'ma'ala. If you get
to somebody who served in the מקדש, Mikdash, who is actually a
כהן kohen that served that did the עבודה, avoda, you don't need
to
go any further. ולא מן הדוכן ולמעלה. v'lo min haduchan u'l'ma'ala. If
you find a לוי who
served in the מקדש, Mikdash, you don't need to go any further.
ולא מן סנהדרין ולמעלה. v'lo min Sanhedrin u'l'ma'ala. סנהדרין Sanhedrin here sounds
like it means סנהדרין גדולה, Sanhedrin Gedola, but this is
according to רש"י Rashi slightly different. But if we say that, it
is it's either any it's either courts in general, סנהדרין גדולה, Sanhedrin
Gedola, סנהדרין קטנה. Sanhedrin Ketana. The גמרא Gemara says סנהדרין קטנה Sanhedrin
Ketana as well. But if we read it as סנהדרין גדולה, Sanhedrin
Gedola, it makes this first part of the משנה mishna nice because
it's three things that happened on the Temple Complex. Anybody who was
involved in stuff on the Temple Complex,
their יחוס yichus is fine.
So I don't understand that. I mean I understand כהנים, I understand
לויים, levi'im, but really סנהדרין Sanhedrin I don't understand because that's all
supposed to be based on your intellectual
acumen. So is a ממזר תלמיד חכם mamzer talmid chacham better? Would
you want this ממזר תלמיד חכם? mamzer talmid chacham?
This is a source for why that's not true. And we will
see that in a because חז"ל Chazal said so. חז"ל Chazal said
you need good to be on סנהדרין גדולה, Sanhedrin Gedola, you need
a good יחוס. yichus We'll see there's problems with this. Yeah.
Is there like a סברא sevara for this?
סברא sevara for why you would need good יחוס?
yichus Yeah, to be a judge?
Yeah, we'll come back to it.
It's coming up I think.
This is רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik said something that might explain it.
But only סנהדרין גדולה Sanhedrin Gedola and not סנהדרין קטנה? Sanhedrin Ketana?
סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, so רב סולובייצ'יק's Rav Soloveitchik explanation which we'll come back
to, or I will say later, only makes sense for סנהדרין גדולה,
Sanhedrin Gedola,
not for סנהדרין קטנה, Sanhedrin Ketana, which is really רב אהרון Rav
Aharon interpreting רב סולובייצ'יק. Rav Soloveitchik.
But they don't
do you know if they don't attribute it other than to say
they're coming up at ע"ו ב 76b that even for the lesser
סנהדרין Sanhedrin of twenty-three judges.
Yeah, so that's in רש"י Rashi here and it's also it's on
the next page. Alright, okay, we'll get there.
We have time, it's only it's not even eight. Okay.
וכל שהוחזקו אבותיו משוטרי הרבים, v'chol shehuchzeku avotav mishotrei harabbim, and anyone
whose father served or was known to the bailiffs,
probably doesn't mean bailiffs which is another job, some sort of lower
judge or judge-like person, גבאי צדקה gabbai tzedaka or someone who was
who was whose job was collecting distributing צדקה, tzedaka, משיאין לכהונה masi'in
likhuna ואין צריך לבדוק אחריהם. v'ein tzarich livdok achareihem. Someone who had
those jobs, they can marry into the כהונה, kehuna, their daughters can
marry into the כהונה, khuna and you don't need to do any
checking. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yossi omer אף מי שהיה חתום עד,
af mi shehaya chatum ed, two different גרסאות girsa'ot here, בערכי הישנה
של ציפורי b'erkei hayeshana shel tzipori
הישנה. hayeshana.
So this is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says there's this city near
ציפורי Tzipori and they had this list of people who either were
could serve as דיינים, dayanim, which is the גרסא girsa without עד,
ed, which is רש"י's Rashi גרסא, girsa, or if they were they
could serve as עדים edim in the court, which is interesting,
and they had a list of them. They were listed down and
those who had good יחוס yichus, already, we don't need to worry
about them. רבי חנינא בן אנטגנוס אומר אף מי שהיה מוכתב באסטרטיא
של מלך. Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos omer af mi shehaya muchtav b'istratya
shel melech. Somebody who was a soldier in the king's army is
the last opinion.
So the king, do you mean the non-Jewish king?
Not clear, it's really weird.
Why would a non-Jewish king care about a Jewish
person's יחוס yichus in his army? Yep, so it's probably a Jewish
king and we're not going to get to that part of the
סוגיא today. Okay. גמרא. Gemara, מאי שנא בנשי בדקי ומאי שנא בגברי
לא בדקי? mai shena b'nashei badki u'mai shena b'gavrei lo badki?
So it's a really good question, why are we only talking about
men checking women and not about women checking men?
Answer.
דכי נשי דכי מנצו בהדי הדדי באריות הוא דמנצו,
dechi nashei deki mintzu bahadi
hadadei b'arayot hu d'mintzu, ואי איתא דאיכא מילתא אית לה קלא. v'i
ita d'ika milta it lei kala. That when women argue with each
other
or when women fight with each other, they accuse each other of
specific immoral acts that they did, that they slept with people they
weren't allowed to sleep with, and thus if there were actually a
problem of יחוס yichus from a previous
generation.
I'll say the second one and then I'll explain it. גברא דנציי
בהדי הדדי ביחסי דנציי אי איתא דאיכא מילתא אית ליה קלא, gavra
d'nitzei bahadi hadadi beyichusei d'nitzei i ita d'ika milta it lei kala,
so when but when men fight with each other, they accuse each
other of having lineage problems, and thus if there were a problem
everyone would know about it. The point being, ר"ן Ran explains
that there's a difference, there's apparently, according to this גמרא, Gemara there's
a difference between the way men and women insult each other. Women
insult each other by accusing each other of bad things. You did
something bad, you're a bad person. When men fight with each other,
it's not you that did something bad, it's your father's a terrible
person, your mother's a terrible person, and they did something bad that
causes you to be bad, but I'm not directly insulting you. The
point being that it's like if I say that your father did
something, or that your mother did something wrong, that means you have
יחוס, yichus I'm saying you have יחוס yichus problems,
and so thus everyone knows you have יחוס yichus problems, or there's
an ערעור irur that you have יחוס yichus problems. If I'm accusing
a woman, you did something wrong, okay fine, your children have יחוס
yichus. problems, you don't have any יחוס yichus problems, or no one
knows about them because I'm not accusing them of them, whether truthfully
or not.
So, does that explain better? Yeah.
Okay, it's a bit of a strange explanation, but that's what the
גמרא Gemara. says and I think the ר"ן Ran makes sense here.
It's the ר"ן Ran on the רי"ף. Rif. Okay. ואי איהי נמי
תבדוק ביה בדידיה. v'ei ihi nami tivdok beih b'dideih.
Why isn't, still, why doesn't she check him? Says the גמרא, Gemara,
that doesn't explain everything. מסייע ליה לרב דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב
לא הוזהרו כשרות להינשא לפסולים. mesayei lei l'Rav d'amar Rav Yehuda amar
Rav lo huzharu kesheirot l'hinasei l'psulim. The answer being, no, this משנה
mishna. helps רב's Rav opinion. רב's Rav opinion is that there's no
איסור for women to marry men who are פסולים לכהונה. psulim l'khuna.
And so if we're saying that women don't have to check the
men for פסולי כהונה psulei khuna. in their backgrounds, then this fits
with רב's Rav opinion that there's no איסור for a woman to
marry men who are פסולים לכהונה. psulim l'khuna.
I mean, wouldn't they want to anyway, you know, to have a
good marriage to the family?
Well
if it's, let's say it's a ישראלית Yisraelit marrying a man
who's in the כהונה and he might be a פסול כהונה, psul
khuna, does it matter so much?
I mean, but given all the emphasis, you'd think that people would
care about this one way or the other.
Maybe so they might have checked them but there's no קנס שקנסו
חכמים knas shekanszu chakhamim according to תוספות's interpretation, though this is a
big big problem for רמב"ן's interpretation, which is why we're going to
leave it aside for the moment.
Okay. רב אדא בר אבא תני ארבע אימות
שהן שתים עשרה.
Rav Adda bar Abba tani arba imot shehen
shtem esrei.
That actually you need to get, that he has a different version
of the ברייתא Braita of the משנה, mishna or he has a
ברייתא braita which is a variant on it, that it's not four
which is eight, it's four which is twelve. על כל
זו מוסיף לדוק עוד אם
למעלה al kol zu mosif lidok od em l'ma'ala that you need
to get another one of...
one further in every point, he says.
Another version says,
תנא מתניתין תני ארבע אימות שהן שש עשרה tana matnitin tani arba
imot shehen shesh esrei that you need to go to four sides
and then you need to get even another one
further
beyond that.
Is it direct maternal or is it the paternal side of that
mother? No,
so
I think the way they do it is that they have pairs
and so it's אם ואם em v'em אם ואם em v'em אם
ואם... em v'em...
yeah, this guy's diagram has two more.
Yeah, it just goes back like because what we saw in every
point, the way we got to eight...
Is it direct maternal?
No, so we also have אבי אביה... avi aviha... we're going through
the paternal lines but
the end
branches end up being maternal lines of specific people. So maternal lines
of the mother
entirely,
the maternal grandfather, and both lines of the father. So you're going
back everywhere.
But what's interesting about it is that this first ברייתא's braita, the
only one that doesn't have an additional pair. It just says an
additional person.
What are you checking exactly?
You're checking if they are ממזרים or פסולי כהונה. Okay. בשלמא
לרב
אדא בר אבא
bishlama l'Rav Adda bar
Abba this...
because basically you can like rely on... I mean... is there a
fact? Like how are you gonna know? You're gonna have to actually
find two עדים edim that say there's a problem?
No idea. I don't know. I don't know.
Because like what are the standards for proof over here?
That's a good question.
Generation to generation?
Which is what we end up like... this is a really good
question, I really don't know the answer to that question.
And this is a רבנן rabanan enactment?
This is totally דברי חכמים. divrei chakhamim. בשלמא לרב
אדא בר אבא מוקי לה
בלוויה ובת ישראל
bishlama l'Rav Adda bar Abba moki
lah bilviya u'vat Yisrael אלא מתניתין נימא פליגא. ela matnitin neima pliga.
So this... Or worse, רב אדא בר אהבה's Rav Ada bar Ahava
opinion that you go back one more works, because that works in
the משנה mishna. where it says עוד אחד. od echad. So you
only go back one more. You only add one onto those ארבעה
שמונה. arba shemona.
What I don't understand is how come you're not going the other
way. Like that's the אבי אמה, avi ima, right? You do אם
אבי אמה. em avi ima. Why don't you do the father of
אבי אמה, avi ima, then the mother on those sides too?
We could just get into the, I think the, that's getting into
the weeds of the סוגיא, which I don't have totally
shuzer or afi right now.
So we've got to move on. Sorry. So the גמרא says that
רב אדא בר אהבה's Rav Ada bar Ahava version of the, רב
אדא בר אהבה's Rav Ada bar Ahava ברייתא braita, works as referring
to the לובייא ובת ישראל lubiya u'bat yisrael from the משנה. mishna
The משנה mishna said עוד אחד od echad by לובייא ובת ישראל,
lubiya u'bat yisrael,
and so he works when he gets four which is twelve, because
you add one more.
But for this other ברייתא, baraita this סתם ברייתא מתניתא, stam braita
matnita,
נימא פליגא. neima pliga. So this sounds like it's, it's חולק cholek
on the משנה. mishna, לא. מאי עוד אחד? mai od echad? זוגא
אחד, zuga echad, that you actually add a whole another pair, which
as I thought made a little more sense. You had pairs, so
you add another pair when you go to בת ישראל. bat yisrael.
So לובייא ובת ישראל, lubiya u'bat yisrael, עוד אחד od echad means
עוד זוגא אחד, od zuga echad, אמא Ima ואם אמא. ve'em ima,
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar
Rav Yehuda
amar Rav, זו דברי רבי מאיר. zo divrei Rabbi Meir. This is
all according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, the
משנה mishna and these other versions of the משנה mishna, are according
to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, and this is
how we hold, כל משפחות בחזקת כשרות הן עומדות. kol mishpachot bechezkat
kashrut hen omdot. Everybody has a חזקת כשרות. You don't need to
do this checking.
Then what are these things
about...
wait a minute, I can go over to the shelf. Sometimes this
edition has like fancy עין משפט Ein Mishpat in the back, but
this one doesn't. Let me go look at it quickly.
It's
איסורי ביאה י"ט. Issurei Biah Yud-Tes. What's the הלכה? halacha? איסורי ביאה
י"ט Issurei Biah Yud-Tes there. י"ט י"ז. Yud-Tes Yud-Zayin. י"ט י"ח. Yud-Tes
Yud-Chet. י"ח, Yud-Chet, okay.
כל משפחות בחזקת כשרות עומדות, kol mishpachot bechezkat kashrut omdot, מותר לישא
מהם לכתחילה. mutar lisat mehem lechatchila. אף על פי כן אם ראית
שתי משפחות שמתגרות זו בזו, af al pi chen im ra'ita shtei
mishpachot she'mitgarot zu b'zu, that's a way of determining if somebody... a
משפחה שקרא עליה
ערער.
mishpacha shekora aleia
ir'ur. Haven't gotten there yet. That's what it is. Is that somebody
has, I say you have a problem, then I have to do
the checking.
If not, then you don't have to check.
And he says the ערער ir'ur is והוא שיעידו שנים שנתערב בהן
ממזר או חלל, vehu she'ya'idu shnayim shenitarav bahen mamzer o chalal,
that we have a rumor that two people were made, so there's
עדות edut from some sort of information that there is a ממזר
או חלל שנתערב mamzer o chalal shenitarav in this משפחה, mishpacha, או
שיש בהן עבדות הרי זו ספק ומשפחה קוצים היא לא ישא ממנה
אשה עד שיבדוק עליה ארבע אמהות שהן שמונה. o sheyesh bahen avdut
harei zo safek u'mishpacha kotzim hi lo yisa mimena isha ad sheyivdok
aleha arba imahot shehen shemona. So that's when you have to do
the checking is when there's a, somebody, עדים edim say that there's
a problem in this family.
Meaning, not that they know for sure, otherwise it'd be עדות edut
and then you're done with your checking. Right. So it's two people
are saying, yeah, you know, we heard a problem.
Yeah. Okay.
איני? ini? Is this really וחכמים? vachachamim? והא אמר רב חמא בר
גוריא אמר רב משנתנו כשקורא לו ערער. v'ha amar Rav Chama bar
Gurya amar Rav mishnateinu k'shekoreh lo ir'ur.
This אמורא amora says that the משנה, mishna which we thought was
according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and not וחכמים, vachachamim, is when
there's a, somebody says there's a problem, not just סתם stam you
have to do the בדיקה bdika. of the כנס, knas, but that
there's, somebody says there's a problem then you have to do the
בדיקה. מתני הא לא מתני הא. matni ha lo matni ha.
So the אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav,
which says the משנה mishna. is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but there
is a, but there's an opinion of וחכמים vachachamim which doesn't hold
like the משנה, Mishna. that person can't hold according to the second
אמורא's opinion of רב חמא בר גוריא אמר רב. Rav Chama bar
Gurya amar Rav. So there's two opinions of רב Rav. and they
are mutually exclusive. That's one answer. הא ולאו מניה? ha v'lav minei?
איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri,
there's another way of, there's another version of the second statement of
רב. Rav, אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, the first statement
again. זו דברי רבי מאיר וחכמים אומרים כל משפחות בחזקת כשרות הן
עומדות. zo divrei Rabbi Meir v'chachamim omrim kol mishpachot bechezkat kashrut hen
omdot. So the משנה is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but we have
a ברייתא וחכמים braita v'chachamim which says not like the משנה. But
then we, but then אמר רב חמא בר גוריא אמר רב אם
קורא עליו ערער צריך לבדוק אחריה. amar Rav Chama bar Gurya amar
Rav im koreh alav ir'ur tzarich livdok achareha. וחכמים מודה לרבי מאיר
vachachamim modeh l'Rabbi Meir that if, as רמב"ם פוסק, Rambam posek, somebody
says there's a problem in the family, עדים edim come and say
we heard there's a problem in this family, you still have to
do the בדיקה. So when you have this version of the second
opinion of רב, Rav then they work together and you can hold
by both. And that, and רמב"ם פוסק Rambam posek that way because
that's how רמב"ם Rambam. understands the כלל of הלכה כבתראי. halacha k'batrai.
Good? Yes.
Rambam says just... that's it.
Yeah, yeah, which is the second, which is the second version of
אמר יהודה אמר רב, Amar Yehuda Amar Rav, of חמא בר גוריא
אמר רב. Hama bar Guria Amar Rav. Okay. אין בודקין מן המזבח
ולמעלה Ain bodkin min ha-mizbe’ach u-lema’lah ויתקא דמתניתין, ve-itka d’matnitin, מאי טעמא?
mai ta’ama? אי לאו דבדקוהו לא הוו מסקי ליה. I lav de-badkuhu
lo havu maskei leh. He wouldn't have been involved to begin with.
So they already did the checking. So you don't have to once
you find out that somebody was in the was working in the
מקדש, Mikdash, you don't have to do any more checking, that checking
was already done at some point. ולא
מן הדוכן ולמעלה Ve-lo min ha-duchan u-lema’lah about לויים, Levi’im, מאי טעמא?
mai ta’ama? דאמר מר ששם היו יושבים מיחסי כהונה ומיחסי לוייה. De-amar
mar she-sham hayu yoshvim meyuchasei kehuna u-meyuchasei leviyah. Same point, the people
who were on the דוכן duchan in the מקדש, Mikdash, they were
already already had good יחוס yichus? to be כהנים and לויים. Levi’im.
You would only have had such people to be on the דוכן
duchan to begin with. They have good יחוס. yichus? We know there's
good יחוס yichus for this person as well. ולא מן הסנהדרין ולמעלה.
Ve-lo min ha-Sanhedrin u-lema’lah. מאי טעמא? Mai ta’ama? Why is it okay
why when somebody was serving on a major court that they have
יחוס? yichus. דתני רב יוסף כשם שבית דין מנוקים בצדק כך מנוקים
מכל מום. De-tani Rav Yosef keshem she-beit din menukim be-tzedek kach menukim
mi-kol mum. Rav Yosef is that just as they are clean in
justice, they were also themselves clean of any blemish.
So but basically really saying you don't have anyone check, but like
God made it work out that way?
No, I don't think we're saying... listen that's one way of reading
this point, but I think this creates this דרשה drasha creates a
requirement to do the checking at some point.
Meaning not to do the checking,
why does it say the same way that the because אי לאו
דבדקוהו i lav de-badkuhu they couldn't have been, you know, on the
סנהדרין? Sanhedrin?
Because we need the we need this ברייתא, we need this דרשה
drasha, to explain this. We need the דרשה drasha to explain why
that would be the case, because you had the question, why a
סנהדרין Sanhedrin only needs to be people who are חכמים ונבונים? chachamim
u-nevonim? Why is there any idea that there should be יחוס? yichus.
And we say there's a דרשה drasha, that there should be יחוס
yichus? or there's a statement, not a דרשה, drasha, I'm sorry.
We haven't seen the דרשה drasha yet. That's the next line. But
then there's a real the real דין from חז"ל Chazal that they
have to be מנוקים מכל מום, menukim mi-kol mum, which apparently includes
the מום mum of פגם יחוס. pegam yichus. אמר מרימר מאי קרא?
כולה יפה רעייתי ומום אין בך. Amar Mareimar mai kra? Kulach yafah
ra’ayati u-mum ein bach. You you my lover beautiful and you have
no blemish, meaning you the court, you the you the זקנים zekenim
of ישראל Yisrael are so beautiful and you have no blemish.
Which is funny because like שיר השירים Shir ha-Shirim is talking about
how beautiful everyone is and you know like עיניך בריכות בחשבון שערך
כעדר העזים שגלשו מן הגלעד einayich bereichot be-cheshbon se’arech ke-eder ha-izzim she-galshu
min ha-gil’ad and now here we're saying it doesn't
mean anything physical, it means יחוס. yichus, Whereas most of the שיר
השירים Shir ha-Shirim is not about anything like יחוס.
yichus Except in this דרשה, in this דרשה, I know, I know,
fine.
And and this is by our tradition that that was written by
someone who married a lot of non-Jewish wives. That's right.
Okay. אימא מום ממש? Eima mum mamash? אמר רב
אחא בר יעקב
אמר קרא והתיצבו שם עמך.
Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov
amar kra ve-hityatzevu sham imach. Does this talk about an actual מום
mum on the body?
And how do we know that it's not we use this as
a proof for the יחוס? yichus And so now explain
now explaining why we say that. אמר רב אחא בר יעקב אמר
קרא, Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar kra, maybe the שיר השירים
Shir ha-Shirim is talking about a physical blemish and it's not talking
about issues of יחוס, yichus so we have a different quote. אמר
רב אמר קרא והתיצבו שם עמך. Amar Rav amar kra ve-hityatzevu sham
imach. Just a second. This is... this is ויאמר ה' אל משה
אספה לי שבעים איש מזקני ישראל אשר ידעת כי הם זקני העם
ושוטריו ולקחת אותם אל אהל מועד והתיצבו שם עמך.
Vayomer Hashem el Moshe esfah li shiv’im ish mi-ziknei Yisrael asher yadata
ki hem ziknei ha-am
ve-shotrav ve-lakachta otam el ohel mo’ed ve-hityatzevu sham imach. That they should
stand there with you and the דרשה is עמך בדומין לך, imach
bi-domin lach, that the people that משה Moshe chooses as the זקנים
zekenim need to be דומין לך, domin lach, need to be דומה
למשה domeh le-Moshe in so far as they don't have יחוס yichus
problems. Great. ודילמא משום שכינה? Ve-dilma mishum shechina? Maybe that means that
it has something to do with the שכינה. shechina. Just a second.
סנהדרין שבאותה שעה Sanhedrin she-be-otah sha’ah says רש"י Rashi וצריכה להיות מיוחסין
משום שכינה ששכינה על שם נבואן נעשו שם. u-tzrichah lihyot meyuchasin mishum
shechina she-shechina al shem nevuan na’asu sham. That it's not an issue
of יחוס yichus
לדורות, le-dorot, it's really just for them because the שכינה, shechina, the
presence of God was actually there with the זקנים zekenim in the
days of משה. Moshe. And so that group of people needed to
be דומה למשה, domeh le-Moshe, but later groups of people don't need
to be דומה למשה domeh le-Moshe and so we have a different
answer. אמר רב נחמן אמר
קרא והקל מעליך ונשאו אתך
Amar Rav Nachman
amar kra ve-hakel me-alecha ve-nas’u itach which is the same
idea. שדומין לך. She-domin lach. ונשאו אתך בדומין לך. ve-nas’u itach bi-domin
lach. Like the ones before. Right. So we go back to the
original point about the זקנים zekenim which is from יתרו Yitro himself
which has to be דומין לך domin lach actually to משה, Moshe,
not about the שכינה, shechina, but just about דומין למשה domin le-Moshe
in their being free of any יחוס yichus problems.
That answers that question. Okay. כל מי שהוחזקו אבותיו משוטרי הרבים, Kol
mi she-huchzeku avotav mi-shotrei ha-rabim, back to the משנה. Anyone whose father
was part of the public service of this kind, whatever it is.
Exactly. דיינים בעלמא שאינם ממנים עשרים ושלוש של סנהדרין קטנה. Dayanim be’alma
she-einam memanim esrim ve-shalosh shel Sanhedrin ketana. למימרא דלא מוקמינן מפסולים
*Lemeimra
d'lo mokminan mipsulim*. This is to say that we don't have פסולים
*psulim* as דיינים *dayanim*. ורמינהו *U'remi'nhu*. This is a problem. הכל כשרים
לדון דיני ממונות ואין הכל כשרים לדון דיני נפשות dinei nefashos. *Hakol
k'sherim ladun dinei mamonot v'ein hakol k'sherim ladun dinei nefashot*. That we
have a ברייתא *braita* or a משנה *mishna* hey just a minute
ברייתא *braita* which says that everybody can actually be a דיין dayan.
*dayan* for דיני ממונות *dinei mamonot*, but not everybody can be for
דיני נפשות *dinei nefashot*. So why are we saying that you can
be a דיין dayan, *dayan* for דיני ממונות *dinei mamonot* seemingly the
שוטרי רבים *shotrei rabim* that has to you can't be פסול *pasul*
if you're going to do that? ואוינה בה *Va'avina bah* but we
have a סוגיא *sugya* about that source. הכל *hakol* there. הכל כשרים
*Hakol k'sherim* comes to include what? לאתויי מאי *L'atuyei mai*? ואמר רב
Rav יהודה *V'amar Rav Yehuda* לאתויי ממזר *l'atuyei mamzer*. That this includes
ממזר *mamzer*. So that so we know that there's a problem. אמר
אביי Amar Abaye. *Amar Abaye* בירושלים *B'Yerushalayim*. So it's only the שוטרי
רבים בירושלים *shotrei rabim b'Yerushalayim* that we can that we can base
this off of because the שוטרי רבים *shotrei rabim* in general which
includes these דיינים *dayanim* for דיני נפשות *dinei nefashot* includes ממזרים *mamzerim*.
אפילו ממזרים *Afilu
mamzerim*. אביי Abaye *Abaye* has to explain that when the משנה *mishna*
is talking about שוטרי רבים *shotrei rabim* that these sort of דיינים
*dayanim* for דיני ממונות *dinei mamonot* it means the דיינים *dayanim* of
דיני ממונות *dinei mamonot* בירושלים *B'Yerushalayim* דוקא *davka*. וכן תני רבי שמעון
בר זבידא בקידושי דבי לוי בירושלים *V'chein tani Rabi Shimon bar Zevida
b'kidushei d'bei Levi b'Yerushalayim*. קידושי דבי לוי *Kidushei d'bei Levi*.
Not sure. ירושלים Yerushalayim, מפינהו כל
דייני *Yerushalayim mipinhu kol dayanei*.
I don't know.
רש"י *Rashi* doesn't say anything so I'm not sure what this is
actually.
It was the academy of לוי *Levi* which beside the corpus of
ברייתות *braitot* from רבי חייא *Rabi Chiya* and רבי אושעיא *Rabi Oshaiya*
another collection of those of לוי *Levi*.
Oh, קידושי *Kidushei* is a place?
It
can be an academy, a something called a
a collection of oh sorry so it's not just people who were
שוטרי רבים בירושלים *shotrei rabim b'Yerushalayim* it's just the list of people
from the academy of לוי *Levi* in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. הבנתי *Hevanti*.
I never understood that קידושי *kidushei* means academy.
I think בי לוי *Bei Levi* is קידושי *kidushei* but it's a
list of the קידושי *kidushei* is this list of people I think.
Okay.
ירושלים *Yerushalayim* apparently ירושלים
*Yerushalayim* was very careful about יחוס yichus *yichus*.
Although they didn't apparently have to be based on this פסוק *pasuk*
based on this ברייתא *braita*. These are Babylonian אמוראים *Amoraim* talking about.
This is true, yeah.
Okay, back to the משנה *mishna*. וגבאי צדקה מסמיים *V'gabai tzedaka masmim*.
So also people who were dealing with צדקה *tzedaka*, they also have
good יחוס yichus *yichus* already. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama? *Mai ta'ama* asks
the גמרא *Gemara*. כיון דמנצי בהדי אינשי דאמר מר ממשכנין על הצדקה
ואפילו Va'afillu? בערב שבת ואי איתא דאיכא איפלוגי איפלוגי קלא *Keivan deminatzi
bahadi inshi d'amar mar memashkenin al hatzedaka v'afilu b'erev Shabbat v'i ita
d'ika iplugi iplugi kala*. So if there were a problem with the
גבאי צדקה *gabai tzedaka* because they're always arguing with people.
How do we know they're always arguing with people?
Because they want to get money out of people.
Because they want to get
people to give a little bit of the money that they owe
to the צדקה *tzedaka* אפילו בערב שבת *afilu b'erev Shabbat*. They're going
around to people five o'clock on Friday afternoon saying you need to
give צדקה *tzedaka*, you need to give something right now. Everybody's going
to get into arguments with them and as we already saw when
people argue with one another they insult their יחוס yichus *yichus*.
So it would have come out by then.
So it would have come out, yeah.
It's not just it's not just arguing with people, רמב"ם Rambam?
*Rambam* פוסק'ס *paskens* based on ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* that they can go to
בית דין *Beit Din* and have your property confiscated if you don't
give צדקה *tzedaka*. And furthermore they even give you lashes if you
don't give to the צדקה *tzedaka*. That's true.
This yeah but so that's in general, this is a specific point
that they're going around Friday afternoon, that's how we know they're going
to fight with people and fighting leads to the revelation of יחוס
yichus. *yichus* problems.
These are more than just the usual שנורר'ס *shnorrers*.
These are not just the usual, these are like these are people
with power, yeah. People don't like them. This is tax collectors, tax
for good reasons. Okay. אושפיזכניה דרב אדא בר אהבה גיורא הוה *Ushpizchanei
d'Rav Adda bar Ahava giyora hava*.
So the host for צדקה *tzedaka* here they say צדקה *tzedaka* collectors
as charity.
Because the צדקה *tzedaka* was a tax.
Oh, it was a tax.
צדקה *tzedaka* was a tax. צדקה *tzedaka* is a חובה *chova* which
is why רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* says you can confiscate your property, all
these things. It's a real tax. There were people who had the
real job to go do it.
It's in the last chapter of מסכת פאה *Masechet Peah*. Yeah, which
nobody ever learns.
It's a very important, it's a great chapter. It's wonderful, yeah.
There's also there's a סוגיא *sugya* in the גמרא *Gemara* about it
that if it's like דבר אחר *davar acher* somewhere, there's somebody goes
to מדינת הים *medinat hayam* you get you can go into their
נכסים *nechasim*
also for something something and דבר אחר *davar acher*. What's דבר אחר
*davar acher*? צדקה *tzedaka*. That they can confiscate confiscating your property is
when you're not even there because you're required to give you your
estate even while you're not there is required to give צדקה *tzedaka*.
So צדקה *tzedaka* in and of itself
should be go to people that really need it.
Yeah, so that's why there's
a גבאי צדקה *gabai tzedaka*. Okay let's go on. אושפיזכניה דרב אדא
בר אהבה גיורא הוה *Ushpizchanei d'Rav Adda bar Ahava giyora hava*.
So the host of רב Rav אדא בר אהבה *Rav Adda bar
Ahava* some sort of story was a גר ger *ger*. והוה קמנצי
איהו ורב ביבי *V'hava kemantzi ihu v'Rav Bibi*.
And he fought with רב Rav ביבי *Rav Bibi*. מר אמר אנא
עבידנא שררותא דמתא,
I will take charge of the town, ומר אמר אנא עבידנא שררותא
דמתא, U-mar amar ana avidna sraruta d'mata, the other one said no,
I’m going to be in charge of the town, I’m going to
be in charge of the local matters. אתו לקמיה דרב יוסף, Atu
lekamei d'Rav Yosef, they came before רב יוסף Rav Yosef to decide
who would actually be in charge of the town. אמר להו תניא,
Amar lehu tenya, so שום תשים עליך מלך, som tasim alecha melech,
he says there's a ברייתא based on the פסוק from דברים. Devarim.
שום תשים עליך מלך מקרב אחיך כל משימות שאתה משים לא יהא
אלא מקרב אחיך.
Som tasim alecha melech mikerev
achecha kol mesimot she'ata mesim lo yehe ella mikerev achecha.
If you give somebody a public job, we interpret the verse to
mean they have to be מקרב אחיך. mikerev achecha. They have to
be considered your fellow, and that's a very apparently a very high
standard. אמר ליה רב אדא בר אבא ואפילו אמו מישראל, Amar lei
Rav Adda bar Abba va'afillu imo mi-Yisrael,
but that includes someone whose mother is a Jew. אמר ליה אטו
מאמו מישראל מקרב אחיך... Amar lei atu mi-imo mi-Yisrael mikerev achecha... ואפילו
אמו מישראל. Va'afillu imo mi-Yisrael. That is מקרב אחיך. mikerev achecha. ואפילו?
Va'afillu? ואפילו?
It's a good question.
Did I go too quickly?
ואפילו אמו מישראל. Va'afillu imo mi-Yisrael.
That's considered No. So he brings the opposite opinion that מקרב אחיך
mikerev achecha
excludes someone who only whose mother is מישראל. mi-Yisrael. So that's not,
he's not called אחיך. achecha. He's a ישראל Yisrael but he's not
אחיך. achecha.
I mean he has to be both mother and father?
Yes. אמר ליה רב יוסף Amar lei Rav Yosef no, אמו מישראל
מקרב אחיך קרינא ביה. imo mi-Yisrael mikerev achecha karina bei. You're wrong,
you misread the, you don't know the דרשא. drasha. הלכך רב ביבי
דגברא רבא הוא וליעיין במילי דשמיא, Hilkach Rav Bibi de-gavra rabba hu
u-li'ayen bemilei d'shmaya,
so he'll take charge of the religious matters of the town. ומר,
U-mar, and this other person, דאושפיזכניה דרב אדא בר אבא, de-ushpizchanie de-Rav
Adda bar Abba, ליעיין במילי דמתא. li'ayen bemilei d'mata. He'll deal with
the non-spiritual matters of the town. אמר אביי. That's interesting. It is
interesting.
הלכך מאן דמשרי
צורבא
מרבנן באושפיזכניה ר' אשרי כרב אדא בר אבא דידע למהפיכי ביה בזכותיה.
Hilkach
man de-mashrei
tzurba
merabbanan be-ushpizchanie re'ashrei ke-Rav Adda bar Abba de-yada le-mapichei bei bizchutei.
אביי learns out of this מעשה a different idea, that if you're
going to host a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham in your house, you
should have him be a certain kind of תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
like רב אדא בר אבא Rav Adda bar Abba who knows how
to argue for the merit of his host. רבי זירא מטפל בהו.
Rabbi Zeira metapil be-hu. רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira
did good by גרים, gerim. says the גמרא. רבה בר אבוה מטפל
בהו. Rabba bar Avuha metapil be-hu.
רבה בר אבוה also did good by גרים. Everyone was nice. ובמערבא
אפילו ריש קורי לא מוקמי מנייהו. U-ve-ma'arava afillu reish korei lo mokmei
minaihu.
But in המערבא, ha-ma'arava, afillu רייש קורי... reish korei... but in the
West, in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, they wouldn't even make them a
ריש קורי, reish korei, which is someone who is in charge of
the weights and measures of the market. So they have very, they
wouldn't allow them to have any power in מערבא. ma'arava. בנהרדעא אפילו
ריש גרגותא לא מוקמי
מנייהו. Be-Neharde'a afillu reish gargouta lo mokmei minaihu. That is לאשקויי בי
תשלוחין מים שהם של
רבים. le'ashkutei bei tashlachin mayim
she-hem shel rabbim.
So they're not even in charge of the town's farm work, the
irrigation of the town. Quickly, רבי יוסי אף מי שהיה... Rabbi Yose
af mi she-haya...
Ah,
right. The next opinion is רבי יוסי אמר אף מי שהיה עד
בארכי ישנה של ציפורי Rabbi Yose omer af mi she-haya ed be-arkei
yeshana shel Tzippori
or just חתום בארכי ישנה של ציפורי. chatum be-arkei yeshana shel Tzippori.
So why is that the case? Asks the גמרא, מאי טעמא? דייקי
ומחתמי, Dayakei u-machtmei,
because in ישנה דציפורי yeshana de-Tzippori they would check and be very
careful and then they would write people
down to be, whether there's a חילופי גרסאות chilufei girsa'ot here of
whether it's an עד ed or
whether it's a דיין.
Okay, but if it's an עד, ed, why do you need to
be so יחוס yichus. to be an עד? ed?
Because in ישנה דציפורי yeshana de-Tzippori they were weird.
We've already seen this in ירושלים, they were special careful about יחוס
for no particular reason. In apparently ישנה דציפורי yeshana de-Tzippori they could've
been careful about יחוס for no particular reason. I don't know why.
There's a lot about יחוס that doesn't quite make sense to me
or I think to any of us here.
Now,
let's go back to the issue that came up here sort of
silently, which is that there's apparently a problem for a גר to
be a דיין, especially on the סנהדרין גדולה, Sanhedrin Gedola, which we
already see
in רמב"ם. Rambam: Where is it in
רמב"ם? Ah, here it is. So רמב"ם פוסק paskens this way in
פרק שני מסנהדרין הלכה א': Perek Sheni me-Sanhedrin Halacha Alef: אין מעמידין
בסנהדרין בין בגדולה בין בקטנה אלא אנשים חכמים ונבונים. Ein ma'amidin be-Sanhedrin
bein bi-gdola bein bi-ktana ella anashim chachamim u-nevonim. You would think he
would stop there. Nice smart learned people. מופלגים בחכמת התורה בעלי דעה
מרובה. Muflagim be-chochmat ha-Torah ba'alei de'a merubba. They know a lot of
תורה, they know a lot of other things.
Okay fine, same idea. יודעים קצת משאר חכמות. Yod'im k'tzat mi-shear chochmot.
They know a little bit about other things as well. כגון רפואה
וחשבון ותקופות ומזלות ואיצטגנינות ודרכי המעוננים וקוסמים ומכשפים והבלי עבודה זרה וכיוצא
באלו, Kegon refua ve-cheshbon u-tekufot u-mazalot ve-itztagninut ve-darchei ha-me'onenim ve-kosemim u-mechashefim ve-havlei
avoda zara ve-chayotzei be-elle, just a little bit.
just the little things that I, רמב״ם *Rambam*, also know, כדי שיהיו
יודעים לדון אותם *kedei sheyihyu yod'im ladun otam*, so they should know
also how to judge these things. Makes perfect sense. ואין מעמידים בסנהדרין
*v'ein ma'amidim b'Sanhedrin* based on our גמרא *Gemara* in other גמרות *Gemoras*,
אלא כהנים לויים וישראלים המיוחסים הראויים להשיא לכהונה *ela Kohanim Leviyim v'Yisraelim
hamiyuchasim hara'uyim l'hasi l'khuna*, שנאמר והתייצבו שם עמך *shene'emar v'hityatzvu sham imakh*,
just one of the פסוקים *psukim* here, דומים לך בחכמה וביראה וביחס
*domim lakh b'chochma u'v'yira u'v'yachas*. Where he got יראה *yira* from I
don't know, it's not in this גמרא *Gemara*. יחס *yachas* is in
this גמרא *Gemara*.
Now, יחס *yachas* vs יחוס
*yichus*. It's the יחוס *yichus* issue.
Now, the רמ״ך *Ramakh* questions here,
can't say the whole thing, but what's
the bottom line on it? Bottom line is they need to be
really, really smart people with good יחוס *yichus*.
So how does that relate to the converts?
How does it relate to the converts? They don't have good יחוס
*yichus*.
They don't have it, which
is a big problem which we're going to explain as we go
on. But first there's another note I want to make here, which
is that the רמ״ך *Ramakh*, רבי משה כהן *Rabbi Moshe Kohen* I
think, who was one of the first, the first person to write
strictures on the משנה תורה *Mishneh Torah*, he was Provençal, said I
don't know why these people need to know חשבון ותקופות ומזלות *cheshbon
u'tkufot u'mazalot*. Why do they need to know all this astronomy stuff?
So the כסף משנה *Kesef Mishneh* says of course they need to.
עיבור שנה *Ibur Shana*, they need to do קידוש החודש *Kiddush HaChodesh*.
What's your problem? Of course they need to know these things, which
is interesting to me because the רלב״ג *Ralbag* in שמות *Shemot* has
an interesting פירוש *peirush* on החודש הזה לכם *HaChodesh hazeh lakhem*. So
everybody החודש הזה לכם *HaChodesh hazeh lakhem*, it's up to you, it's
what you choose is what's real on Earth is what's real in
שמים *Shamayim*. He says no, החודש הזה לכם *HaChodesh hazeh lakhem*
means what you choose. Why is it in your hands? It's not
certain that in every generation there's going to be a wonderful, incredible
astronomer like the רלב״ג *Ralbag* who was a fantastic astronomer for the
13th century, 14th century—14th century.
To the degree that the first part of the fifth book of
מלחמות השם *Milchamot Hashem* of רלב״ג *Ralbag* was immediately translated into Latin,
has a totally separate manuscript tradition. It's his book on astronomy, which
is a major astronomy book in the Middle Ages.
So it's not certain that there's going to be basically a רלב״ג
*Ralbag* in every generation and so החודש הזה לכם *HaChodesh hazeh lakhem*,
whatever you choose because you're not going to get it quite right.
So you're going to make errors and even when you make slight
errors, it's going to be okay. I give you that power to
make those slight mistakes, says the רלב״ג *Ralbag*.
Now, so this is one רמב״ם *Rambam*.
The big problem with this רמב״ם *Rambam* is that in פרקי אבות
Avos. *Pirkei Avot*, who's listed as people who were
part of the chain of tradition and thus according to another tradition?
שמעיה ואבטליון Shmaya ve-Abtalyon *Shemaya v'Avtalyon*. שמעיה ואבטליון Shmaya ve-Abtalyon *Shemaya v'Avtalyon*
were part of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin *Sanhedrin* and they were גירים *geirim*
according to a משנה *Mishna*, according to the גמרא *Gemara* in סנהדרין
Sanhedrin *Sanhedrin* I think.
And רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* was at least from a convert family.
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* was also from a convert family, which we
see from another story that he doesn't have זכות אבות *zechut avot*,
which זכות אבות *zechut avot* also comes up in the next סוגיא
*sugya* which we're not going to look at right now. So how
in the world do we explain the presence of שמעיה ואבטליון *Shemaya
v'Avtalyon* in the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* when they are גירים *geirim*, and it's
very clear from the גמרא *Gemara* and it's very clear from the
רמב״ם *Rambam* that it's problematic for גירים *geirim* to be on the
סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*?
So the תומים Tumim, *Tumim* has this question. The תומים Tumim *Tumim*
is רב Rav יהונתן אייבשיץ *Rav Yehonatan Eibeschutz* on חושן משפט *Choshen
Mishpat* and he, it's in סימן ז סעיף קטן א *Siman Zayin
Sif Katan Alef*, he explains as follows: that the סנהדרין גדולה *Sanhedrin
Gedolah* has two jobs. One is that there's, there's דיני נפשות *dinei
nefashot* that they need to do. They need to do דיני נפשות
*dinei nefashot*, they need to judge זקן ממרא *Zaken Mamre*, they need
to do this, that, and the other thing, and that גירים *geirim*
aren't כשרים *kesherim* to judge those issues. Are or are not? Are
not. So שמעיה ואבטליון *Shemaya v'Avtalyon*, so
they can't do דיני נפשות *dinei nefashot*.
But the בית דין הגדול *Beit Din HaGadol* also has a second
job, which is to be עיקר תורה שבעל פה *ikar Torah sheba'al
peh*, which is the לשון *lashon* of the רמב״ם *Rambam* in הלכות
ממרים *Hilchot Mamrim*, which we're going to see in a second. And
that job of being בעלי המסורה *ba'alei hamesorah* and being the מופלגים
בחכמה *muflagim b'chochma*, knowing תורה *Torah*, knowing all these things and teaching
and deciding what the law is—not a specific case—that is totally unproblematic
and it's even better for שמעיה ואבטליון *Shemaya v'Avtalyon* to be there
because they were the גדולים שבדורם *gedolim shebdoram*.
I'm sorry, so they were on the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*?
They were on the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* and then they would leave when
דיני נפשות *dinei nefashot* were going on, they would add two other
people on to the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*.
So the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* may have had more than seventy?
So no, so it's like seventy minus two plus two. You would
add two back in, or you would,
it would be like a larger bench.
You'd have a larger bench.
This is done in some courts today where they bring in temporary
judges.
They do bring in temporary—yes, so the Supreme Court doesn't do that,
but other people do that and then you have like people sitting,
whether they're doing it in groups or they're doing it en banc.
So the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* always sat en banc. But the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*
has two jobs and they were even the most important for the
job of being בעלי המסורה *ba'alei hamesorah* and being in charge of
תורה שבעל פה *Torah sheba'al peh*, but they were פסול *pasul* for
the job of doing דיני נפשות *dinei nefashot*, so they couldn't be
involved in that. רב Rav סולובייצ׳יק *Rav Soloveitchik* says something similar but
slightly more elegant. So רב Rav סולובייצ׳יק *Rav Soloveitchik* says that again,
there are two jobs of the סנהדרין הגדולה *Sanhedrin HaGedolah*. One
is
to be
in charge of the מסורה *Mesorah*, they have to be עיקר תורה
שבעל פה *ikar Torah sheba'al peh*. And so now we'll quote the
רמב״ם *Rambam* in הלכות ממרים *Hilchot Mamrim*. פרק א הלכה א: בית
דין הגדול שבירושלים הם עיקר תורה שבעל פה והם עמודי ההוראה ומהם
חוק ומשפט יוצא לכל ישראל ועליהם הבטיחה תורה שנאמר על פי התורה
אשר יורוך זו מצות עשה וכל המאמין במשה רבינו ובתורתו חייב לסמוך
מעשה הדת עליהם ולהישען עליהם.
Beis Din HaGadol shebiYerushalayim heim ikar Torah sheba'al peh veheim amudei ha-hora'ah
umeheim chok umishpat yotzei le-chol Yisrael ve-aleihem hivtichah Torah shene'emar al pi
ha-Torah asher yoru-kha
zo mitzvas aseh ve-chol ha-ma'amin be-Moshe Rabbeinu ube-sorato chayav lismoch ma'aseh ha-das
aleihem ulehisha'ein aleihem. They are חז"ל means people in the סנהדרין הגדול.
Sanhedrin HaGadol.
This aspect of legislation and deciding what the תורה is and means,
that's one side. That is the what רב Rav Lichtenstein uses, it's
the הלכתי תורני hilchati Torani part of the job of the סנהדרין
הגדול. Sanhedrin HaGadol. The other part is expressed in סנהדרין פרק ה
הלכה א Perek Hey Halacha Aleph in the רמב"ם: אין מעמידין מלך
אלא על פי בית דין של שבעים ואחד ואין מושיבין סנהדריות קטנות
לכל שבט ושבט ולכל עיר ועיר אלא על פי בית דין של
שבעים ואחד ואין דנין לא את השבט שהודח כולו ולא את נביא
שקר ולא את כהן גדול בדיני נפשות אלא בבית דין הגדול.
Ein ma'amidin melech ela al pi beis din shel shiv'im ve-echad ve-ein
mosivin sanhedriyos ketanos lechol shevet vashevet ulechol ir va'ir ela al pi
beis din shel shiv'im ve-echad
ve-ein danin lo es hashevet shehudach kulo velo es hanavi sheker velo
es kohen gadol bedinei nefashos ela beveis din hagadol.
These aspects that you set up a king, you set up other
judges, what רב Lichtenstein explains in רב Soloveitchik's idea as being the
משפטי טקסי, mishpati tekesi, the legal ritual aspect part of the סנהדרין
הגדול's Sanhedrin HaGadol job, that's a different thing. When they're doing that,
they're being the נציגי כלל ישראל. nitzigei Klal Yisrael. And when the
סנהדרין הגדול Sanhedrin HaGadol is being representative of the body of Israel
of כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, they need to have a higher יחוס
standard to be in there.
And what was the first part? The first part, how do you
term it?
It's the הלכתי תורני. hilchati Torani.
So in the aspect of הלכתי תורני, hilchati Torani, יחוס is irrelevant.
Because אפילו ממזר תלמיד חכם afilu mamzer talmid chacham is גדול מכהן
גדול, gadol mikohen gadol, which is what we said earlier. It's more
important to be a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham than it is to
have good יחוס. כהן גדול kohen gadol is the best יחוס.
But to be נציגי כלל ישראל, nitzigei Klal Yisrael, you need to
be נציגי נבחרי העם, nitzigei mivcharei ha-am, is how we're seeing it.
And so רב Lichtenstein following this distinction of the two roles, slightly
formulated differently than the תומים, רב Lichtenstein explains that in the formal
role, the formal ritual role as נציגי כלל ישראל, nitzigei Klal Yisrael,
שמעיה ואבטליון would have been problematic and so they would not have
been part of that.
And for the הלכתי תורני hilchati Torani role, obviously they were the
most important people because they're the people listed in אבות. רב Soloveitchik
apparently also has the idea according to his distinction that the body
unlike what we said by the תומים that they would go out,
that שמעיה ואבטליון would just not, they would leave, someone else would
replace them when the
סנהדרין הגדול Sanhedrin HaGadol would do דיני נפשות. רב Soloveitchik says these
two parts don't need to be the same body. So it's like
you can have the legislative body and you can have the judicial
body, which is what we have in American government. In the Israeli
government, the
בית דין עליון Beis Din Elyon in the secular government sits as
different bodies. There's the בית דין הגבוה לצדק Beis Din HaGavoah LeTzedek
which is where you go for human rights issues. There's the, I
don't remember what the other one is called, but there's like the
בית משפט העליון Beis Mishpat HaElyon which is like the last court
of appeals. It's the same group of people, they sit in different
bodies, they sit as different forms, they wear different hats. סנהדרין הגדול
Sanhedrin HaGadol according to רב Soloveitchik is different, that it's you have
those two aspects which are both important and they're both called סנהדרין
הגדול, Sanhedrin HaGadol, but it could be made up of different people
entirely. There could be a totally different set of 71 because maybe
when you're being
נציגי כלל ישראל, nitzigei Klal Yisrael, there's 140 people.
There's 140 people called סנהדרין but they do two different things. Okay,
that's what we'll stop for today. Let's go.